Guide to the Records of the 1948 Election Voting Study in Elmira, New York 1939-1972 (bulk 1948-1954) MS 196
New-York Historical Society
Records of the 1948 election voting study in Elmira, New York
1939-1972 (bulk 1948-1954)
New-York Historical Society
Berelson, Bernard, 1912-1979
MS 196
14.88 Linear feet in 14 record cartons, one document box, and 67 phonograph records
The records of the 1948 election voting study in Elmira, New York, include the documentation underlying the book Voting: A Study of Opinion Formation in a Presidential Campaign, co-authored by Bernard R. Berelson, Paul F. Lazarsfeld, and William N. McPhee. In this study, the authors sought to analyze how citizens made up their minds as to how to vote. The study centered on the 1948 U.S. presidential contest between Harry S. Truman and Thomas E. Dewey, using the "normal community" of Elmira, New York, as the test site. The records include the completed questionnaires administered to over 1,000 participants at four points in time during and after the election campaign, study administration files, analyses, background reference materials, local newspapers and other periodicals from Elmira, and phonograph recordings of topical radio broadcasts, especially those of Fulton Lewis, Jr. and of Meet the Press.
Arrangement Note
The collection is organized in three series:
Series I. General Project Documents, 1948- 1972 (bulk, 1948-1954)
Series II. Questionnaires, 1948-1950
Series III: Reference Materials, 1947-1948
Biographical/Historical Note
The records of the 1948 election voting study in Elmira, New York, include the documentation underlying the book Voting: A Study of Opinion Formation in a Presidential Campaign, co-authored by Bernard R. Berelson, Paul F. Lazarsfeld, and William N. McPhee. The authors positioned their study as one of a series conducted by various scholars in the context of different elections from 1940 to 1952. Their overall aim was to attain a "better understanding of the processes of democratic elections," particularly in terms of how citizens make up their minds as to how to vote (Voting, vii). The 1948 presidential election pitted the Democratic Party candidate and incumbent U.S. President Harry S. Truman against the Republican Party nominee and New York Governor Thomas E. Dewey. But the primary and general campaigns were also notable for the range of other viable candidates or potential candidates from across the political spectrum, from Henry A. Wallace on the left to Strom Thurmond on the right. Further, this was the first presidential election since the end of World War II, at a time of great changes domestically and internationally, and the first since the early 1930s without Franklin D. Roosevelt at the head of the Democratic ticket. Throughout the election season, Truman was viewed as such a vulnerable candidate that the mass media conveyed the expectation that Dewey would defeat him, yet Truman won, elected by 2.5 million votes. It was in this volatile political environment that Bernard Berelson and his team launched their study of voters and voting.
Berelson acquired his Ph.D. in 1941 from the Graduate Library School at the University of Chicago. His thesis focused on the mass media's effect on the formation of public political opinion. In 1944, he joined the Bureau of Applied Social Research at Columbia University, where its founder, Paul Lazarsfeld, was also interested in the power of mass media and its influence on public opinion. In 1944, Lazarsfeld and Berelson's work The People's Choice was published, a study of the 1940 election, using Erie County, Ohio, as the site of analysis. Berelson returned to Chicago in 1946, but kept in contact with Lazarsfeld, eventually planning a study of the upcoming 1948 election.
Berelson and Lazarsfeld chose Elmira (including the surrounding unincorporated towns) as the site of their 1948 study because it represented a "normal" community from which generalizations might be drawn. Specifically, Elmira was of moderate population size; independent but not isolated from any metropolitan district; socially and economically stable; had good media exposure with a typical educational and cultural environment; had a balanced labor and industrial situation; was politically competitive; and had a typical ethnic composition. They divided a map of Elmira into 816 segments, numbering them in a serpentine fashion, and selected every third segment, yielding 271 segments to visit. Within the segments, all households (about 6,000) were noted with the final sample of 1,267 households chosen from those. Interviews were then attempted, with a final sample size of respondents totaling 1,029.
Berelson and Lazarsfeld decided to employ the so-called "panel method" in Elmira by which the same individuals were interviewed at multiple points over time in order to assess the dynamics of their decision making process. Accordingly, the study team implemented four "waves" of questionnaires in 1948: in June, before the party nominees were decided at the July conventions; in August, after the conventions and before the campaigns' fall push; in October, as the election drew near; and in November, right after the election. (The collection also holds questionnaires from 1950, but Voting does not seem to refer to these and it is unclear what their relationship to the initial study is.) Not all members of the panel participated in all four waves for various reasons, but 746 (72%) did. 907 (88%) participated in three of the four waves. Only 43 (4%) participated in June and then dropped out.
Subsequent to the fieldwork, William N. McPhee, who was a sociologist and invented a computer simulation model for voting, joined the Elmira study team. McPhee used a computer to help analyze the results of the survey and he wrote several chapters of Voting, which was published in 1954, six years after the election.
(The principal sources for this note were Voting: A Study of Opinion Formation in a Presidential Campaign, documents in the collection and Wikipedia.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
The source of the collection is somewhat uncertain, but appears to have been donated in December 1972 by Columbia University's Bureau of Applied Social Research.
Related Archival Materials Note
Columbia University Libraries holds the Bureau of Applied Social Research Records, 1944-1976. These records include several files concerning the 1948 Elmira study. These can be found at:
Series I (Project Index), at http://findingaids.cul.columbia.edu/ead/nnc-rb/ldpd_5012632/dsc/1/
and Series III (Reports), at http://findingaids.cul.columbia.edu/ead/nnc-rb/ldpd_5012632/dsc/3/
Scope and Contents Note
The records of the 1948 election voting study in Elmira, New York, include the project documents compiled, most likely, by Bernard R. Berelson, and that underlie the publication Voting: A Study of Opinion Formation in a Presidential Campaign. These documents include the project's files concerning administration, planning, funding, methodology, field interviewer instructions, data coding, and analysis. The collection includes an extensive number, perhaps all, of the completed questionnaires and interviews from the study. These include the four "waves" of questionnaires implemented in 1948 and discussed in Voting, probing voter attitudes toward the Presidential candidates, their perspective on key national and international issues, and influences on their voting choice. There are also two additional sets of questionnaires from 1950 that relate, although in an unclear manner, to the Elmira study. The collection also includes examples of mass media with potential influence on voting behavior in Elmira, especially local newspapers and other periodicals and recordings of radio broadcasts over local station WENY. Most of these recordings are of the syndicated national program of conservative newscaster, Fulton Lewis, Jr.
Voting -- United States.; Voting research; Maps.; Research (documents); Newspapers.; Memorandums.; Questionnaires; Elmira (N.Y.); Sound recordings; Radio addresses, debates, etc.; Correspondence.; Elections -- United States -- Case studies.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1948.; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972; Columbia University. Bureau of Applied Social Research
- Series I. General Project Documents, 1939-1972 (bulk 1948-1954); 5 Linear feet
  Arrangement Note
  In 2017, in large part the project files were found in no particular order by the processing archivist. Accordingly, the arrangement of the series was established by the archivist. The series is divided into eight groups: administrative documents, questionnaire drafts, survey documents, code books, analysis documents, book drafts, reference documents, and miscellaneous. Each group is arranged in chronological order. Most folder labels were transcribed from the original folder. For loose or unlabeled documents, the processing archivist assigned a label; these are indicated in [brackets].
  Scope and Contents Note
  The series includes seven types of documents related to the Elmira study: administrative documents, questionnaire drafts, survey documents, code books, analysis of the data collected in the surveys, book drafts, and reference documents. The administrative documents include memos, correspondence, and minutes concerning the planning of the 1948 election study, communication with other scholars to develop study details, progress reports, and letters to companies and research organizations to gather support. The series includes early drafts of each wave of the questionnaires, indicating their relationship to the study plan; survey documents, including maps of Elmira, record of interviews, and survey instructions for the field team; code books and related instructions for analyzing the outcome of the survey by using computers; the analysis of the data and survey outcomes, including memos and calculations; and drafts of each chapter of Voting, dust jackets, and the final version of the book. The series also includes the academic reference materials bearing on the Elmira study, including other scholars' analyses of the effects of mass media during presidential campaigns and the formation of public opinion in the late 1930s to early 1940s.
  The series also includes a group of miscellaneous documents that are unrelated or indirectly related to the Elmira project. These documents include Bernard Berelson's diplomas and individual correspondence with the University of Chicago; radio studies in Italy, Greece, and Turkey; a health survey from Columbus, Ohio; and a student survey in 1965.
  - Administrative Documents (Box -, Folder -)
  - Lazarsfield Memo on Politics, 1940s? (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Documents & Intro & First Wave (3 folders), 1947-1948 August (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - General (2 folders), 1948 April-June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Publicity Releases, 1948 April-October (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rand Corporation B.B [Bernard Berelson], 1947 August-1951 May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - AAPOR [American Association for Public Opinion Research] Research Development and Committee (2 folders), 1948 May-1951 April (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Correspondence Preceding & During the Campaign, 1948 May-November (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence [Bernard Berelson] (3 folders), 1948 January-1951 May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12-14)
  - Elmira [Memorandums and Questionnaire drafts], 1948 May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Progress Report [Bernard Berelson], 1948 August (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Elmira-Current [Memorandums], 1948 November-December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cornell Inventory, 1948 December 31 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - [Minutes of Meeting], 1949 March 14 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - [Course] #492 Communication & Public Opinion, 1949 March-May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - Project- Correspondence with Cornell, 1949 November-1950 May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - Change- Chapter Notes, 1950s~? (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence re: Analysis, 1950 October-1953 December (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
  - David Gleicer, 1950 May-1951 January (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
  - Organization F: Democratic Theory, 1951 June 28 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
  - [Elmo Roper Joins NBC During 1952 Election], 1952 January 10 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26)
  - Handbook for Politics: McPhee's Memo to Lipset, Circa. 1952 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence [to Universities], 1953 March-April (Offsite-box 1, Folder 28)
  - Questionnaire Drafts (Box -, Folder -)
  - Correspondence and Memos re: Study & Questionnaire Construction (2 folders), 1948 May-1950 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Wave I Questionnaires from 1st to Final Draft (2 folders), 1948 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 31-32)
  - Wave I Blank Callback Sheets and Questionnaires, 1948 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 33)
  - Wave II Questionnaire from 1st to the Final Draft, 1948 July (Offsite-box 1, Folder 34)
  - Wave II Pre-test Draft, 1948 August (Offsite-box 1, Folder 35)
  - [Wave II Blank Second Questionnaires], 1948 August (Offsite-box 1, Folder 36)
  - Wave III Questionnaires, 1948 September (Offsite-box 1, Folder 37)
  - Wave III, 1948 September (Offsite-box 1, Folder 38)
  - Wave III Questionnaires from the First to the Final Draft, 1948 September-October (Offsite-box 1, Folder 39)
  - Wave IV Questionnaires, 1948 November (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
  - Post-Election Questionnaires - Not Used, 1948 November (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Wave IV Blank Questionnaires, 1948 November (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1950 Elmira Follow-up Study, 1950 April-July (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Survey Documents (Box -, Folder -)
  - Maps of Elmira (1 of 2 folders), Circa 1948 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    These folders include the maps showing the segments that the study team divided Elmira and the surrounding communities into for purposes of establishing the interview sample.
  - Maps of Elmira (2 of 2 folders). Oversize, 1945-1947 (Oversize small)
  - Listing Instructions, 1948 May 14 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
  - Selection of Respondent, 1948 June (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sample: Townships & Wards, 1948 June-August (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - Instructions for Interviewers (2 folders), 1948 June-September (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Listing Sheets: Segments 1-300 (6 folders), 1948 May (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11-16)
  - [Selected Series of Questionnaires] (2 folders), 1948 June-November (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Interviewer Comments. Wave I, 1948 June (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
  - Background & Intensive Interviews, 1948 July (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - Elmira Intensive Interviews: Communications, 1948 August (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - Interviews 2a, 1948 August (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - Intensive Interviews: Inter-Group Relations - Ethnic, Religious, Racial, 1948 June-September (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
  - Intensive Interviews: Union Leaders, 1948 June- August (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
  - [Letters to Respondents, Returned by Post Office], 1948 November (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
  - ["Safari to Elmira"], 1948? (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
  - Code Books (Box -, Folder -)
  - Code Books (5 folders), Circa 1948 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27-31)
  - Coding Copies of Code Books, Circa 1948 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 32)
  - Coding Instructions and Interview Guides, 1948 June-September (Offsite-box 2, Folder 33)
  - Editing & Coding Instruction. Memos re: Coding, 1948 June-1950 March (Offsite-box 2, Folder 34)
  - Analysis Documents (Box -, Folder -)
  - History of Democratic Party, 1948 June (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
  - [Pre-1948 Election Survey and Analysis] (2 folders), 1948 July (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - [Documents Sent to Bernard Berelson], 1948 October (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
  - [Newspaper Clippings and Radio Speeches] (3 folders), 1948 October (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - [Newspaper Clippings on the Election], 1948 October (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
  - Organizations Classified by Major Functions, Circa 1948 June (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
  - [Memos and Survey Analysis], 1948 November-1949 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
  - Actual Vote Records, 1948 December-1949 January (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
  - Trend [Respondent Type and Effects of Mortality Analysis], Circa 1949 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
  - Gilliam Long-term Change Memos, Circa 1949 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
  - McCarthy: Sampling Procedure in Elmira, 1949 October 27 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
  - Thielens [Preliminary Report on the Elmira Mortality], Circa 1950 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
  - Factors Analysis Study, Circa 1950 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
  - [Memos, Correspondence & Analysis] (2 folders), 1950 March-November (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17-18)
  - Various Memos Re: Analysis, Circa 1951 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
  - Interest in Election, 1951 April (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20)
  - Suggetions For Analysis: Mostly PFL (Lazarsfield) at Various Times, Circa 1951 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 21)
  - Content Analysis (2 folders), Circa 1951-1952 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - CMTN [Communication] & Discussion: Used (2 folders), Circa 1952 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 24-25)
  - Materials Used in Perception Section (4 folders), Circa 1952 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 26-29)
  - Robbie Rule Model, 1953 April (Offsite-box 3, Folder 30)
  - Material from Cornell & Ecological Data, 1953 October 2 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
  - Book Drafts (Box -, Folder -)
  - Organization of Book, 1950 August 22 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 32)
  - Grounds for Decision Chapter, 1950 November (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
  - Perception Chapter (2 folders), 1950 December (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34-35)
  - Early Chapter Drafts (2 folders), 1950 December-1951 March (Offsite-box 3, Folder 36-37)
  - Manuscript. Communication & Discussion Section (2 folders), 1951 February (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38-39)
  - Dean: Unions in Elmira, Circa 1952 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Early Draft of Group Chapter, Circa 1952 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  - Kaplan Draft: Group Homogeneity, Circa 1952 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
  - John Dean: Outline Role of Party, Circa 1952 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
  - Early Draft of Chapter 7 (New Chapter 7), Circa 1952 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
  - J. Dean: Political Parties-Draft, 1952 June (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
  - New Dean Chapter on Parties, 1952 June (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
  - Notes, Memos, Etc. Re: Group Chapter, 1952 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
  - Early Drafts of Issue Chapter (2 folders), Circa 1953 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9-10)
  - Early Draft of Chapter 9, 1953 July (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
  - Notes, Papers, Memos Re: Issue Chapter (2 folders), 1952 January-1953 October (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12-13)
  - [Early Draft of The People's Second Choice], 1954 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
  - 1953 December Draft (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
  - [Dust Jackets of Voting], 1954 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
  - Reference Documents (Box -, Folder -)
  - [An Index of the Papers in Elmira Box 6], Post 1954 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17)
  - Book I (2 folders) [Binder Content], 1950 January-June (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18-19)
  - Book II (2 folders) [Binder Content], 1949 May-1950 June (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Box III (2 folders) [Binder Content], 1949 May- 1950 July (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22-23)
  - Book IV (2 folders) [Binder Content], 1950 July (Offsite-box 4, Folder 24-25)
  - Time of Final Decision, Scott Hunter, Circa 1948 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 26)
  - Anonymous, Communication Analysis, 1948 December (Offsite-box 4, Folder 27)
  - Anonymous, Paper on Local vs. National Elections, Circa 1949 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 28)
  - Birnbaum, The Feeling of Influence, 1950 August (Offsite-box 4, Folder 29)
  - Crosetti,The Process of Short-Term Change, Circa 1950 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
  - Baxter, Crosstabulation of Interpersonal Influence Questions, Circa 1949 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 31)
  - Dinerman, 1948 Votes in the Making, 1948 December, 1972 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
  - David Gold Paper, Circa 1950 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
  - Gray, Class Structure and Vote in Elmira, Circa 1949 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
  - B. Hockey Papers (2 folders), 1950 February (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - Index of Political Predisposition, Circa 1950 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
  - Kaplan, Sandusky Replication, Circa 1950 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
  - Awareness of Political Conflict, Circa 1949 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
  - McPhee: A Dysfunctional Analysis, Circa 1953 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
  - H.Senft, Changers Communication, 1950 February (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
  - "Certain Hypotheses with Regard to Movies and Radio", 1939 September (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
  - [Studies on Film], 1939 September-1945 May (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
  - "Public Communications and Public Opinions", 1941 April (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13)
  - "Analyzing the Content of Mass Communication", 1942 September (Offsite-box 5, Folder 14)
  - "Effect of Chicago Sun on War Attitudes", Circa 1944 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)
  - [Memo on Magazine Study], 1944 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16)
  - [Documents on Radio Analysis], Circa 1946 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 17)
  - Reports on Chicago Material, Circa 1946 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 18)
  - [Effect of Mass Media Analysis], 1946 September (Offsite-box 5, Folder 19)
  - "To What Extent Are Newspaper Columnists Read?", 1947 March (Offsite-box 5, Folder 20)
  - Memo on General Problem and Related Content Analysis, 1947 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 21)
  - Audience Analysis, Circa 1947 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 22)
  - [Studies on Communications Control], Circa 1947 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 23)
  - The University of Chicago Magazine, 1949 January (Offsite-box 5, Folder 24)
  - "An Analysis of the 1948 Presidential Pre-Election Polls", 1949 August (Offsite-box 5, Folder 25)
  - N.Y State Business Facts Elmira Area: 1954 Supplement (Offsite-box 5, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous (Box -, Folder -)
  - [Degrees of Bernard Berelson], 1936, 1941 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 27)
    Includes Berelson's B.A. and Ph.D. Also includes a contract concerning the publication of What Reading Does to People.
  - Correspondence-Chicago, 1944 October- 1946 April (Offsite-box 5, Folder 28)
  - [Analysis of Radio in Turkey] (2 folders), 1949 June- November (Offsite-box 5, Folder 29-30)
  - [Analysis of Radio in Italy], 1949 September (Offsite-box 5, Folder 31)
  - [Analysis of Radio in Greece], 1949 September (Offsite-box 5, Folder 32)
  - Reports on Turkey and Greece, 1949 October- 1950 January (Offsite-box 5, Folder 33)
  - [Columbus Community Survey-Health] (2 folders), Circa 1948 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 34-35)
  - [Students' Questionnaire], 1965 April (Offsite-box 5, Folder 36)
    Includes one survey of a 10th grade student from Madison High School in New Jersey concerning public high school education.
- Series II. Questionnaires, 1948-1950; 8 Linear feet
  The series is arranged with the 1948 questionnaires followed by the 1950 questionnaires. The 1948 questionnaires are arranged in numerical order, based on the segment number written on each questionnaire. All four waves of the 1948 questionnaire are found together. Each of the two waves of the 1950 questionnaires are arranged separately, each wave also in segment number order.